If doing that means no one will cry, then...
Idealism's End
THE ANSWER
You certainly took your time getting here, Emiya Shirou.
It finally occurred to me.
There can't be two of those pendants.
It was originally—
That's right.
After your life was saved, you carried it for the rest of your days.
A memento of Tohsaka Rin's father, unique in all the world.
When summoning a Heroic Spirit, a catalyst is needed.
But Tohsaka Rin did not have one for the invocation.
Because of that,
she assumed that she had no connection to the Servant she summoned.
But no Heroic Spirit is summoned by chance.
A link is always required between summoner and spirit.
If Rin had no catalyst, that means...
Yes.
The summoned Heroic Spirit,
not the summoner, possessed the catalyst.
The concept of time does not exist
where the Heroic Spirits are recorded.
Heroic Spirits from the past are treated identically to those of the future.
In short...
Yes.
It is possible to summon someone who will exist in the future.
Archer...
Where's Tohsaka?
I handed her over to Matou Shinji when he got here before you.
You what?
Relax, kid.
Leave the little lady to me.
Lancer?
I have my Master's orders, you see.
Keeping her alive has always been my reason for working with you.
Actually, it's been really nice.
It's rare for me to enjoy a task I've been given.
So until this is over, let me look after her.
After that, we'll be enemies again.
Take care of Tohsaka.
Will do.
I shall remain here, Lancer.
Are you serious?
The little lady is your Master now.
I understand that.
But I must bear witness to this battle.
Really now?
Have it your way, then.
"Bear witness," huh?
I'm glad to hear that.
If you interfered now, severing my contract
with Rin would have been for nothing.
Yes.
Come what may, I will not interfere with your battle with Shirou.
But in return, I want you to answer one thing.
Why are you so intent on killing Shirou?
Why do you even ask?
Just as he can't accept me, I can't accept him. That's all.
That cannot be true!
You should embody Emiya Shirou's ideals in the form of a hero.
Why would that ideal reject itself?
Unlike you, I didn't become a hero entirely on my own merits.
I'm nothing but a Guardian who became a hero
by selling his posthumous self.
A Guardian?
Off you go.
What's with the glare?
I see you're as oblivious as ever.
Don't you understand the position you're in?
Try looking in a mirror.
I'd say you're the oblivious one here.
Oh, drop the tough act.
It's pathetic.
Unbelievable.
Looks like nothing I say will get through to you.
Good! That's more like it!
So you've finally figured out that you belong to me?
Man, I love legs that have just enough muscle.
It'll make playing with you all the more fun.
Ow!
Sorry about that, punk.
My fist went flying before my words.
L-Lancer?
Hey.
Wh-What are you doing here?
Save it.
I'll have those ropes cut in a jiffy.
After that, do as you like.
Go to the hall and stop those idiots from fighting,
or slip out the back and go home. Your call.
Lancer, behind you!
What?
That's quite enough, Lancer.
I did say to work with them,
but I never said to get emotionally invested.
Kirei?
A Guardian?
I heard that, after their deaths, Guardians become part of the Counter Force that protects humanity.
Even if you followed a different path to become one,
you are nonetheless a Heroic Spirit.
That's where you're mistaken, Saber.
Guardians don't protect humanity.
They're simply sweepers.
Archer?
You're right...
I did become a hero.
Just as the man called Emiya Shirou always wished,
I became a true champion of justice.
A champion of justice...
And that is exactly why.
I know that becoming one was a mistake.
That man's life had absolutely no value.
No value?
None.
Surely you understand, Saber.
After all, you want to change the past—
to take back your decisions—more than anyone.
Saber?
What?
You never asked her what her wish was?
Why she desires the Holy Grail enough
to commit herself to this pointless bloodbath?
Then allow me to tell you. She is—
Archer!
Shirou...
I wanted to use the Holy Grail—the all-powerful granter of wishes—
to undo a decision I once made.
I made a mistake—
one that condemned Britain to destruction.
And I fell before I could change that fate.
That is why I want to win the Grail.
I did not reach my ideal self.
I should never have become king.
But you are different.
Are you not the ideals of Emiya Shirou fully realized?
The realized ideals, huh?
It's true that I did become my own ideal champion of justice.
But as a result, I gained nothing but regrets.
Having made a pact with the Counter Force when alive,
I became a Guardian after my death
and acted on behalf of humanity's Counter Force,
fighting those who disrupted the world's balance.
Obeying my orders,
I killed.
And killed...
And just kept killing.
I killed so many I ceased to care.
For every life I took, I saved thousands.
I fought again and again, whenever I was called upon.
Again,
and again,
and again...
But there was no end to it.
It was never over.
It wasn't as if I dreamed of a world free of fighting.
I just didn't want anyone to cry in the world I knew.
That's when it finally hit me.
The ideal that Emiya Shirou clung to was but shallow idealism.
Why do you say that?
It's impossible to save everyone.
Saving the many means leaving the few to perish.
You should know that well, Saber.
Those who were bound to fall from the seat of happiness,
I quickly cut down with my own hands.
That is the proper course of action for a hero—
for that man's ideal champion of justice.
Saving as many as possible is what a champion of justice does, is it not?
And so, still wishing for no one to die,
I would have one person die for the sake of many.
Even as I said that I couldn't let anyone feel sorrow,
I ultimately drove more than a few to despair.
That is who I am.
That is the Heroic Spirit Emiya's true colors.
Don't you think the world would be better off
if that man died right now?
Kill yourself, Emiya Shirou.
Ow...
Wasn't it my Master's credo to never reveal themselves?
I have no such policy.
In fact, you are the one disobeying orders, Lancer.
I seem to recall ordering you to terminate Archer.
He'll do himself in without any help from me.
More importantly, did you put that kid up to this?
Spare me your baseless accusations.
We have an arrangement.
We've reached a mutual accord for the sake of winning the Grail.
Figures.
I always knew you wouldn't die that easily,
but why win a harmless loser like Shinji over to your side?
You take him for harmless, do you?
Even in this situation, you remain Tohsaka Rin to the core.
If you were a less capable pupil, this would be less regrettable.
Hang on, Kotomine.
Was that talk about wanting to save your pupil a lie?
Nothing of the sort.
She is an important pawn that I have taken great pains to nurture.
I've spent ten long years deceiving her,
so what fun would it be if she left the battle so easily?
That was why I entrusted her safety to you.
You phony priest.
Participating in a game that you're supposed to oversee is so unfair it's not even funny.
And yet you don't seem all that surprised, Rin.
So you suspected me?
Of course I did.
Though admittedly, it never occurred to me that I'd been tricked from the beginning.
From the beginning?
What?
Oh, when you said, "From the beginning,"
I was wondering how far back you meant.
Kirei, you...
Since after this Holy Grail War began?
Or does the "beginning" you speak of
refer to the previous Holy Grail War?
I see...
So it was you who killed my father.
Of course.
After all, he was my beloved teacher.
Catching him by surprise was child's play.
What's the matter?
Now that you know what you are, why hesitate?
Archer,
you have not gone against your ideals.
Did you not simply lose your way
when the very ideals you upheld betrayed you?
Were that not the case,
you would not consider killing yourself atonement for your sins.
Oh, this is rich.
Atone for my sins?
Don't be a fool, Saber.
You're right: I was betrayed and deceived countless times.
You can't expect anyone to understand a man willing to lay down his life for others.
In the end,
I was set up as the mastermind behind a conflict and sent to the gallows.
You must be lying, Archer...
That was how you died?
If I had any sins, surely I atoned fully for them in that moment.
It's not as if I ever wanted gratitude.
I never wanted to be celebrated as a hero, either.
I simply wanted an outcome where everyone was happy.
But that was never given to me—
neither in life nor afterward.
I knew that Guardians were, essentially, automated defense mechanisms.
That after death, those who offer themselves to be Guardians
are removed from the cycle of death and rebirth,
becoming tools that safeguard human history.
I thought it would still be worth it if I could save someone—
one person who was in trouble.
But it's nothing like that!
You bastard!
I hope you get lost in the afterlife, you asshole!
Even Hell wouldn't want anything to do with you!
Purgatory would call you a bad influence and pass you off somewhere else!
But I'm sure you'd just hate it in Heaven,
so why don't you string yourself up outside the Pearly Gates, you eunuch?!
Kotomine, you know that Tohsaka's been given to me, right?
I'm the only one who has business with her.
No, I have business with her as well.
You see, I require her to become the Holy Grail.
Once Archer and Saber are gone, the time will finally be right.
I do not want her to lose her freshness by resisting needlessly.
Let us get this over with quickly.
Lancer, dispose of that trash.
The vessel has no need of a heart.
Guardians don't save humans.
Guardians simply clean up their messes.
They're beings that use their power to negate events that have already transpired—
disasters of humanity's own making.
They're butchers that kill anyone who threatens the human world, with no regard for good and evil.
What a joke.
How is that any different from when I was powerless?
To save as many lives as possible...
Are you saying that you were unable to fulfill that wish even once?
I am.
I've culled the very people I wanted to save.
That was where my ridiculous ideal of becoming a champion of justice ultimately lead.
I'm sick of cleaning up after humanity.
But as a Heroic Spirit, I'm doomed to repeat that for all eternity.
I've already given up my agency.
The only way I can think of to disappear completely would be...
If you kill a human destined to be a hero,
you think it will be as though that hero was never born?
My only hope has been to wait for that opportunity—
for this day to come.
It will not work.
You already exist as a Guardian.
You are outside the confines of time.
Even if you eliminate this Shirou, you will not disappear.
Perhaps.
But it isn't beyond the realm of possibility.
If I destroy not only his flesh but also his spirit,
at the very least, his mistaken
"champion of justice" will not appear in this world.
What's the matter, Emiya Shirou?
If I'm so unacceptable to you,
kill yourself right here and end it!
Shirou!
What's the matter, Lancer?
Your target is a little girl.
Killing her should be simple.
I refuse.
I can't obey you this time.
What?
If you want to make me do it,
you'll have to use a Command Spell.
You leave me no choice, then.
In that case, I order you by my Command Spell:
Sorry, Emiya-kun.
I'm leaving this fight before you.
Kill yourself, Lancer.
Lancer!
Archer, do you have regrets?
Of course I do.
Then I guess we're two different people after all.
What?
No matter what happens, I'll never regret a thing.
And that's why I'll never accept you.
If you're my ideal,
then I'll just have to get rid of that misguided ideal myself!
That way of thinking is how all of this began.
One day, you will reach the point where you become me.
I won't.
That day will never come.
That's true.
I suppose it won't.
If you won't run from here, in any event, you have no future.
Archer!
It's okay, Saber.
Thanks.
But please, stand back.
This is a fight I need to have.
Trace...
...on.
Can you keep up with my blade works?
If your precision wavers even slightly, it will spell your death.
If I am destined to turn to ash and bones
I will take your heart.
Once useless, always useless, I suppose.
I admired the wish to save someone, because it was beautiful!
I don't want to become one. I will become one!
Next Time